UZMAR DE JESUS GOMEZ YANEZ

CURRICULUM VITAE



MSc Scientific Computing and Data Analysis

PERSONAL STATEMENT

Hands-on experience applying Machine Learning algorithms. Excellent usage of GNU / Linux systems and knowledge of object-oriented programming languages such as Python and C++. I have worked in the academic field as a teacher assistant, teaching mathematics, computer science, physics and other topics at a university level. Good understanding of algorithms, data structures, bayesian statistics, etc. Experience managing containerized applications using Kubernetes.

PERSONAL DATA

Address: Edinburgh, Scotland Phone: +44 7704 613361

EMAIL: uzmar.gomez@hotmail.com
LINKEDIN: www.linkedin.com/in/uzmargomez
GITHUB: https://github.com/uzmargomez

RESEARCHGATE: https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Uzmar-Gomez

EDUCATION

2022 | MSc in Scientific Computing and Data Analysis, Department of Computer Science, Durham University,

Durham, United Kingdom.

2021 Specialization: Earth and Environmental Sciences

Dissertation: "GPU Programming with Standard C++"

Description: Used NVIDIA HPC SDK compiler suite to accelerate ExaHyPE's Finite Volume scheme, a

generic code base to simulate wave equations. The resulting code was benchmarked against an OpenMP GPU offloading code port of exactly the same code structure, and we report

on some problems and benefits of the new C++ software stack.

Advisor: Dr Tobias Weinzierl

GRADE: Distinction Detailed List of Grades

2018 | BSc in Physics, Faculty of Science, National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), Mexico City,

Mexico.

2011 Dissertation: "Numerical Study of Vlasov Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric"

Description: Creation of a finite differences scheme that evolves the relativistic Vlasov equation on a

black hole metric background, assuming this is an advective equation, with velocities

dependent both on time and position.

Advisor: Dr Miguel Alcubierre

OVERALL SCORE: 9.37/10 Detailed List of Grades

LANGUAGES

ENGLISH: C1 Level - IELTS (2021)
SPANISH: Mothertongue

FRENCH: Basic

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming Languages | Python, C++, Fortran, Julia

Machine/Deep Learning | TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, Facebook Prophet, ARIMA, SARIMA, LDA, PCA,

Kmeans, KNN, Neural Networks, Recommendation systems, Classification

and Regression problems

Serving Triton, Seldon Core, TFServing

Databases | SQL, MongoDB | Docker, Kubernetes | GNU/Linux, Windows

Web Backend | Flask

Web Frontend | HTML (Plotly Dash), Bootstrap

Version Control | Git

Parallel Computing | C++ Standard Algorithms, CUDA Python

Data Visualization | Plotly Dash, Qlik, Tableau

GCP Tools | BigQuery, BQ ML, Compute Engine, Composer (Airflow), Artifact Registry,

Kubernetes Engine, Storage, Data Studio, Kubeflow, Data Fusion, Cloud

Build, VertexAl

Kubernetes Infrastructure | Kubectl, Helm, Kustomize, Ansible, ArgoCD, Grafana, Prometheus,

HashiCorp Vault, MetalLB, NGINX Ingress, Istio Gateway, GSLB

EXPERIENCE

Short Description

Mar 2023 - Present. ML R&D Programmer at Rockstar Games. Deployment and administration of the on-prem Kubernetes infrastructure for the ML Animation Team, using tools such as Kubectl, Helm, Ansible, ArgoCD, Grafana, Hashicorp Vault, and others.

Sep 2022 - Mar 2023. Associate ML R&D Programmer at Rockstar Games.

Jul 2020 - Jan 2022. Data Scientist at Rackspace Technology. I helped migrate data from on-premises servers to the GCP cloud. I worked on churn prediction models that used features related to the COVID19 spreading aside from other business-related features to predict customer attrition, this work includes the development of the model using XGBoost, as well as the deployment of it using Kubeflow and the serving via Seldon Core. I was also involved in constructing an SSAS OLAP Cube to be used by the company for inventory-related queries. I worked on NLP tasks, such as extracting themes out of tickets using semantic similarity, by getting embeddings vectors out of sentences with a transformer architecture named Universal Sentence Encoder. Worked on how to translate voice to text. I built two production-level applications using Plotly Dash.

Dec 2019 - Jun 2020. Data Scientist at Softtek. I worked on a face recognition system using a method called Sparse Representation and another one using Neural Networks. I acquired a deep understanding of Neural Networks for Face Detection and Recognition, Image Classification, and Language Processing, among others, as well as some experience in Data Visualization tools such as Tableau.

Sep 2019 - Dec 2019. Data Scientist Trainee at Softtek. I learned about different statistical and machine learning techniques and algorithms to study a wide variety of problems.

Sep 2018 - Dec 2019. I have research experience using the Einstein Toolkit, a software platform created for supporting research in relativistic astrophysics and gravitational physics.

2016 - **2019**. Worked as a Teacher's Assistant. I've given lectures aimed at Computer Science and Physics Students on the following topics:

- Computer Science.
 - https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/102.pdf
- Selected Topics in Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation 1. https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/docencia/horarios/presentacion/295997
- Relativity
 - https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/718.pdf
- Mathematics I for Applied Sciences.
 - http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1118.pdf
- Mathematics II for Applied Sciences.
 - http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1216.pdf

INTERESTS AND ACTIVITIES

Academic

Data Science, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Numerical Analysis, General Relativity, Numerical Relativity, Black Holes.

Non academic

Science Fiction and Fantasy Reading, Videogames, Running, Swimming, Playing Guitar, Traveling.

EXTRA CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

JUN 2022 | Student Representative MiSCaDA Programme

OCT 2021 | Durham University

Provide a link between students and the University Staff. Sit on the Student/Staff Comittee to discuss issues within the department raised by the students

VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

MAY 2022 | Volunteer JAN 2022 | **Durham Foodbank**

Assisted with the distribution of food to people in need.

DEC 2021 | Teacher JUN 2021 | Casa de la Sal

Support children with HIV on various Mathematics and English Language assignments.

SEP 2019 | Teacher

MAR 2019 University Student Council (CEU México)

Provide tools to university students to help develop their academic, professional and personal skills, to facilitate their employment and the definition of their life project.

Mar 2019 | Volunteer

SEP 2018 | Adopt a Talent Program (PAUTA)

Encourage scientific vocation so that those children and adolescents who like science and have outstanding skills, find a space where they can share their interest and learn from each other.

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIP

SEP 2019 | Fellow
JAN 2017 | Thematic Network of Black Holes and Gravitational Waves (Red ANyOG, CONACYT).

DEC 2019 | Student Associate

JAN 2016 Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM.

JAN 2016 | Student Associate

JAN 2015 Institute of Physics, UNAM.

PRESENTATIONS AND POSTER SESSIONS

OCT 11, 2017 | Poster Presentation at LX NATIONAL CONGRESS OF PHYSICS.

Monterrey, Mexico

Presentation of a poster about my undergraduate thesis "Numerical Study of Vlasov Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric".

SCHOLARSHIPS, AWARDS, HONOURS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

2017	Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Proyect
2016	Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT).
2016	Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Undergraduate School
2015	Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT).

REFERENCES

NAME: Dr. Tobias Weinzierl

OCCUPATION: Professor in the Department of Computer Science at Durham University

LINKEDIN: tobias.weinzierl@durham.ac.uk

NAME: Dr. Charles Mueller OCCUPATION: Senior Engineer at Amazon

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/charles-n-mueller/

NAME: Dr. Fernando Herrera
OCCUPATION: Senior Data Engineer at Revolut

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/fernando-jose-herrera-elizalde-76a32790/

NAME: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

INSTITUTION NAME: Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM.

OCCUPATION: Director, Researcher, Teacher EMAIL: malcubi@nucleares.unam.mx

UPDATED ON APRIL 4, 2024

Master of Science in Scientific Computing and Data Analysis

Durham University Grades

Course	GRADE	CREDITS
Project	7.8	60
Professional Skills	7.92	15
Core Ia: Introduction to Machine Learning and Statistics	9.15	15
Core Ib: Introduction to Scientific and High-Performance Computing	7.95	15
Performance Engineering and Advanced Algorithms	7.5	15
Advanced Statistics and Machine Learning: Foundations and Unsupervised Learning	9.0	15
Advanced Statistics and Machine Learning: Regression and Classification	9.15	15
Earth and Environmental Sciences	6.76	30
	Total Credits	180
	GRADE	Distinction

Bachelor of Science in Physics

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) Grades

Course	Grade	CREDITS
Differential and Integral Calculus I	07	18
Algebra	10	10
Computer Science	10	6
Analytic Geometry I	08	10
Differential and Integral Calculus II	10	18
Contemporary Physics	09	6
Vector Mechanics	9	12
Analytic Geometry II	09	10
Mechanics Laboratory	10	6
Collective Phenomena	10	12
Collective Phenomena Laboratory	09	6
Linear Algebra I	10	10
Differential Equations I	08	10
Optics	09	12
Linear Algebra II	10	10
Differential and Integral Calculus III	07	18
Electromagnetism I	9	12
Electromagnetism Laboratory	10	6
Tensor Calculus	9	10
Differential and Integral Calculus IV	07	18
Introduction to Quantum Physics	10	12
Optics Laboratory	10	6
Thermodynamics	09	12
Advanced Mathematics of Physics	10	10
Computational Physics	10	12
Quantum Mechanics	09	12
Complex Variable I	10	10
Selected Topics of Mathematics and Theoretical Physics	10	6
Electromagnetism II	08	12
Electronics Laboratory	10	6
Statistical Physics	10	12
Contemporary Physics Laboratory I	10	6
Complex Variable II	10	10
Analytical Mechanics	10	12
Relativity	09	06
Introduction to Elementary Particle Physics I	10	06
Dynamics of Deformable Bodies	10	12
Atomic Physics and Condensed Matter	09	06
Nuclear and Subnuclear Physics	09	06
Contemporary Physics Laboratory II	10	06
Topology and Differential Geometry for Physics	10	06
Selected Topics of Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation I	10	06
Selected Topics of Computational Physics I	10	06
English Language	AC	00
	Total Credits	418
	OVERALL SCORE	9.37